Guide to the Institute for Health Policy Studies - AIDS Resource Program Records
UCSF Library & CKM
Institute for Health Policy Studies - AIDS Resource Program records
1986-1988
AR 92-20
Institute for Health Policy Studies - AIDS Resource Program
13 cartons, 2 boxes 17.25 linear ft.
University of California, San Francisco. Library. Archives and Special Collections. San Francisco, California 94143-0840
This collection contains the materials collected by the AIDS Resource Program of UCSF's Institute for Health Policy Studies to use as reference materials to meet their goal of providing information and education on the San Francisco Model of HIV/AIDS services and to assist in their analysis of other HIV/AIDS health and social services policies and programs. A large majority of the material in the collection consists of newspaper clippings, magazine and scholarly articles, government publications, grant information. Correspondence, handwritten notes, drafts, and other original materials are scattered throughout the collection.
Access
Collection open for research.
Acquisition Information
The AIDS Resource Program Records were transferred to the Archives and Special Collections by the Institute for Health Policy Studies, a unit of the University of California, San Francisco
Organizational History
Institute of Health Policy Studies The Institute of Health Policy Studies was founded by University of California, San Francisco professor of social medicine and former University Chancellor, Philip R. Lee, M.D., in 1972. It was established as the Health Policy Program with support from the Robert Wood Johnson Foundation, and the University of California. In 1977 the Institute was awarded a five-year grant from the National Center for Health Services Research, Department of Health, Education, and Welfare, as the only national Health Services Policy Analysis Center. In February 1981 the University of California Board of Regents designated the Institute as a UCSF campus-wide organized research unit within the University. As of 1985 the Institute's budget was over $3.5 million and has received grants and contracts from over 30 public and private funding agencies for the support of research, teaching, technical assistance, and dissemination activities. The institute expanded from a small group of faculty members focused on federal health policy to a diverse group of faculty, fellows, and professional research staff who represent a broad range of clinical and social science disciplines and methods. In 2005 IHPS faculty have appointments in all four schools at UCSF (medicine, pharmacy, nursing, and dentistry). The primary goals of the IHPS are: to conduct policy-oriented research and analysis on a wide range of health issues; to apply research findings to health policy issues at the national, state, and local levels; and to provide education and training opportunities in health policy and health services research.
Lee, the founder and original director of IHPS, also served as the first president of the seven-person Health Commission for the City and County of San Francisco, established in January 1985. The commission is the governing body for the Department of Public Health of the City and County of San Francisco, and must approve all public health related budget requests submitted to the Mayor and Board of Supervisors.
AIDS Resource Program Responding to a growing number of visits and requests for information on San Francisco's successful, comprehensive, coordinated AIDS services system, the IHPS submitted a grant of $600,000 to The Robert Wood Johnson Foundation to create the AIDS Resource Program of the Institute for Health Policy Studies, University of California, San Francisco. The grant which funded the ARP ran from January 1, 1986 - December 31, 1988.
Previous to the 1985 grant request the Institute had conducted a series of policy-relevant studies relating to the AIDS epidemic, particularly studies relating to costs and to the organization, management and financing of community-based services. The Institute also initiated several studies on community-based services to help clarify the nature of the community response to the AIDS epidemic. Peter Arno (economics) and Robert Hughes (organizational behavior/sociology) compared New York City and San Francisco's local policy responses to HIV and AIDS. Peter Arno also studied the contributions of the voluntary non-profit sector in San Francisco. Jane Zones (sociology) also produced a study on the responses of individuals that they were informed about the results of their HTLV-III antibody tests.
The project was under the direction of Philip R. Lee, M.D., Director of the IHPS, and Patricia E. Franks was the Project Coordinator. Three members of the Department of Public Health were directly involved in the program: Dr. David Werdegar, Director of Health; Jeffery Amory, Coordinator of the AIDS Activity Office; and Dean Echenberg, Director of Communicable Disease Control. The faculty of the UCSF AIDS Clinical Research Center, directed by Dr. John Ziegler, Professor of Medicine and Director of Education at the VA Medical Center in San Francisco, also played a key role in the project.
The objectives of the AIDS Resource Program were:
(1) to provide information and education about the comprehensive HIV service system in San Francisco to individuals and groups from communities throughout the country to enable them to apply lessons learned in San Francisco to their own institutions, agencies, and communities
(2) to enhance the capacity of service agencies in the community including the San Francisco AIDS Foundation, VNA/Hospice of San Francisco, and the Shanti Project, the San Francisco Department of Public Health, and UCSF to meet the needs of individuals and groups seeking information about HIV programs in San Francisco.
To meet these objectives the AIDS Resource Program preformed five Project activities:
(1) development of educational materials describing San Francisco's HIV programs for use in self- or small-group instruction and for distribution
(2) development of seminars, training sessions, and continuing education programs for physicians, nurses, dentists, and public health administrators on the organization, financing, and delivery of health and social services for persons with HIV, using San Francisco as a model, but including information on other service programs
(3) coordination of visits and technical assistance for health professionals, health care administrators, social service agency directors, health policymakers, and community leaders
(4) detailed analysis of HIV health and social services policies and programs, including cost studies; and
(5) dissemination of information and analyses to public officials, nonprofit agency providers, health professionals, and community leaders throughout the country.
When the AIDS Resource Program ended on December 31, 1988, information about the HIV epidemic had grown to a point where it was no longer practical to clip and catalogue newspaper, journal and magazine articles. Also other non-profit or for-profit groups were producing newsletters and weekly and monthly compendia of information.
In addition, many of the community-based organizations to which AIDS Resource Program staff had provided technical assistance and information had become established with their own staff and special service areas.
However, research into cost and policy issues related to the HIV epidemic remains one of 12 areas of emphasis listed on the IHPS web-site in 2005 with two of the Institute's faculty listing HIV/AIDS as a current research area.
Scope and Content of Collection
This materials in this collection were organized into two general categories: government files and subject files. The government files have been further broken down into four series: SERIES 1: STATE OF CALIFORNIA; SERIES 2: SAN FRANCISCO CITY AND COUNTY; SERIES 3: STATES AND COUNTRIES; and SERIES 4: UNITED STATES (FEDERAL GOVERNMENT).
The government files contain information about government policies, legislation, and other information concerning the HIV epidemic as it related to federal state and local government, as well to the international community. These documents were used for general reference by AIDS Resource Program staff and for analyses of health and social programs, legislation, and policies to provide information and technical assistance to health professionals and community organizations around the country. Several grant proposals for Robert Wood Johnson Foundation (RWJ Foundation) monies, particularly their AIDS Health Services grant programs are found in Series II: San Francisco City and County, Series III: States and Countries, and elsewhere in the collection. The RWJ Foundation (founded by the founder of the Johnson & Johnson company) with its emphases on: assuring that all Americans have access to quality health care at reasonable cost; improving the quality of care and support for people with chronic health conditions; promoting healthy communities an lifestyles; and reducing the personal, social and economic harm caused by substance abuse (tobacco, alcohol and illicit drugs), funded not only the IHPS AIDS Research Project, but many of the other state and local projects represented in this collection.
SERIES 5: SUBJECT FILES contain newspaper clippings, magazine and journal articles, and various written materials on specific topics related to the HIV epidemic. These files were used for general reference and in the production of the AIDS weekly Reader, a compendium of federal, state and local HIV statistics; journal, magazine and newspapers articles, which provided up-to-date information on the HIV epidemic to 70 selected policymakers, researchers, and program managers throughout the nation. This series is arranged alphabetically.
The subject files make up the majority of the collection and, within both the subject and governmental files, a significant portion of the items in the collection consist of newspaper clippings. Another significant percentage of the collection consists of academic papers and reprints from a variety of publications or in typed draft form. Some folders also contain whole periodicals, often newsletters but sometime magazines, proceedings or even books. There are also a significant number of grant proposals and some requests for proposals (RFP's) within the collection. Correspondence between IHPS staff and others, or copies of correspondence between third parties can be found in some folders, as can be a variety of government budgetary, statistical and legislative materials. Publicity materials from various agencies: flyers, pamphlets, press releases, and conference announcements also appear throughout the collection. Handwritten meeting notes and other materials appear periodically and some files contain official organizational minutes or other administrative records. There are also 3 oversize posters, one audiotape, and some slides.
Some of the materials were organized chronologically or reverse chronologically within a given folder, but most had no clear discernable order. For preservation purposes, an attempt was made to isolate the clippings still on newsprint to the front of the file, though some may still be found interspersed among other items. This means that the more original or unique items will usually be found towards the back of the folder, though some folders consist completely of newspaper clippings.
Indexing Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the library's online public access catalog.
AIDS (Disease) California; AIDS (Disease) San Francisco History; AIDS (Disease) Government Policy United States; AIDS (Disease) Social Aspects; AIDS (Disease) Research Government Policy; California. Dept. of Health Services. Office of AIDS; Robert Wood Johnson Foundation; University of California San Francisco. Institute for Health Policy Studies
Related Material
MSS 94-69 San Francisco AIDS Foundation (SFAF) Records
MSS 97-03 Richard Bolen Papers
MSS 2000-06 Nancy (Shaw) Stoller Papers
MSS 94-01 Women's AIDS Network (WAN) Records
MSS 96-31 Angie Lewis Papers
MSS 94-18 John Ziegler Papers
MSS 91-1 Philip R. Woods Papers
IHPS-Tobacco Records (unprocessed?)
Collection Contents
- State of California, 1983-1989; Series 1; 1 carton, 41 folders
  This series consists of files pertaining to AIDS Services within and across California, funded by the State of California and/or effecting the state as a whole, and materials on specific counties, the state college and university systems, and various health and governmental organizations. This includes legislative bills and statewide budgeting, California ballot initiatives (bills qualified for the ballot by voter signatures instead of legislative acts), Actions by other state organizations and by counties within California. Contents include newspaper clippings, reports, budget materials, legislation and responses, reports and scientific articles.
  The majority of statewide materials fall into four subject areas: California Ballot Initiatives (especially Proposition 64 - La Rouche Initiative); the Department of Health Services (DHS), Office of AIDS files; California Legislature files; and State Services Delivery System/Advocacy Groups. The DHS files include a contractor's address list, requests for proposals (RFPs), correspondence, AIDS planning, programs and budget folders, information on alternative tests sites, Medi-Cal costs, and task forces and advisory committees. Also see the "Monthly Field Activities Reports" and the "Quantitative Analysis of AIDS in California." The Legislative files deal the state AIDS budget and AIDS legislation including hearings on various bills. The state delivery system and advocacy group files include files on various local governmental and local health official cooperative associations, the Health Policy and Research Foundation of California, and Lobby for Individual Freedom and Equality (LIFE), as well as the Hemophilia AIDS Project. Of special interest are the index & price list found in the Office of Statewide Health Planning and Development folder and the URSA Institute's "Evaluation of California's AIDS Commission Education Project"
  The majority of statewide materials are followed by the county material which is arranged alphabetically by county from Alameda to Sonoma. Not all counties in the state are represented. There is a single folder of material for each of the counties covered, and a folder for the East Bay AIDS Project following the Alameda and Contra Costa County files, since this group covers both of these counties. The county files are followed by files on several California State Medical organizations (such as the California Association of AIDS Agencies (CAAA), the California Medical Association (CMA) and the California Nurses Association (CNA)) and the University of California (Davis, Berkeley, UCLA) [that are not found in Series II: San Francisco City and County].
  - California State Budget, 1987-1989 (Box:folder 1:1)
  - Federal AIDS Contracts and Grants, 1987 (Box:folder 1:2)
  - Epidemiology - Clippings, 1987-1988 (Box:folder 1:3)
  - Counties - Clippings, 1986-1987 (Box:folder 1:4)
  - Office of the Governor - Clippings & Documents, 1985-1987 (Box:folder 1:5)
  - State AIDS Budget - Clippings & documents, 1987-1989 (Box:folder 1:6)
  - State Policies/Response to AIDS - Clippings & documents, 1986-1988 (Box:folder 1:7)
  - California State Universities - Clippings & documents, 1988 (Box:folder 1:8)
  - California Ballot Initiatives (Box:folder 1:9-15)
    - AIDS Initiatives, 1988 (Box:folder 1:9)
    - Proposition 103, September 1988 (Box:folder 1:10)
    - Proposition 64 - La Rouche Initiative (Box:folder 1:11-15)
      - Conference - "Public Forum on Prop 64" - October 29,1986 at UCSF Sponsored by IHPS-ARC (Box:folder 1:11)
      - Background, 1986 (Box:folder 1:12)
      - UC & State Reports on Prop 64, 1986 (Box:folder 1:13)
      - Clippings, 1986 (Box:folder 1:14-15)
  - Department of Education, 1985-1987 (Box:folder 1:16)
  - Department of Health Services, Office of AIDS (Box:folder 1:17-33)
    - Contractors (Address List), n.d. (Box:folder 1:17)
    - Requests for Proposals, 1986-1988 (Box:folder 1:18-20)
    - Correspondence/Announcements, 1986 (Box:folder 1:21)
    - AIDS Plan, 1985-1988 (Box:folder 1:22)
    - AIDS Programs & Activities, 1987-1988 (Box:folder 1:23)
    - AIDS Budget Recommendations, 1986-1987 (Box:folder 1:24)
    - Alternative Tests Sites, 1987-1988 (Box:folder 1:25-26)
    - Monthly Field Activities Reports, 1985-1988 (Box:folder 1:27-28)
    - Medi-Cal Costs, 1985-1988 (Box:folder 1:29-30)
    - California Health Facilities Commission, ca. 1983 (Box:folder 1:31)
    - Task Forces/Advisory Committees, 1986-1987 (Box:folder 1:32)
    - Quantitative Analysis of AIDS in California, 1987 (Box:folder 1:33)
  - California Legislature (Box:folder 1:34-2:8)
    - AIDS Budget Task Force, 1985-1987 (Box:folder 1:34-36)
    - Assembly Ways and Means Task Force, 1985-1988 (Box:folder 1:37)
    - AIDS Legislation (Box:folder 2:1-7)
      - Assembly Bills, 1985-1988 (Box:folder 2:1)
      - Senate Bills, 1985-1988 (Box:folder 2:2)
      - Legislative Analyst's Office, 1987 (Box:folder 2:3)
      - AIDS Hearings - Senate, 1987-1988 (Box:folder 2:4)
      - Senate Office of Research, 1989; n.d. (Box:folder 2:5)
      - AIDS Hearings - Assembly, 1984; 1987 (Box:folder 2:6)
      - General Legislation, 1986-1988 (Box:folder 2:7)
    - Senate Select Committee on AIDS, 1989 (Box:folder 2:8)
  - State Services Delivery/System/Advocacy Groups (Box:folder 2:9-17)
    - Association of Bay Area Governments, 1986 (Box:folder 2:9)
    - California Association of AIDS Agencies, 1985-1987 (Box:folder 2:10)
    - California Conference of Local Health Officers, 1986-1987 (Box:folder 2:11)
    - Health Officers Association of California, 1986 (Box:folder 2:12)
    - Health Policy and Research Foundation of California, 1987 (Box:folder 2:13)
    - Hemophilia AIDS Project, undated (Box:folder 2:14)
    - LIFE - Lobby for Individual Freedom and Equality, 1987 (Box:folder 2:15)
    - Office of Statewide Health Planning and Development - Index & Price List, 1988 (Box:folder 2:16)
    - URSA Institute: Evaluation of California's AIDS Commission Education Project, 1987 (Box:folder 2:17)
  - California Counties (Box:folder 2:18-32)
    - Alameda, 1987-1989 (Box:folder 2:18)
    - Contra Costa, 1987-1988 (Box:folder 2:19)
    - East Bay AIDS Project, 1984-1988 (Box:folder 2:20)
    - Kern, 1988 (Box:folder 2:21)
    - Los Angeles, 1987-1988 (Box:folder 2:22)
    - Marin, 1987-1988 (Box:folder 2:23)
    - Monterey, n.d. (Box:folder 2:24)
    - Riverside, 1986 (Box:folder 2:25)
    - Sacramento, 1988 (Box:folder 2:26)
    - San Diego, 1986; 1988 (Box:folder 2:27)
    - San Joaquin, 1987 (Box:folder 2:28)
    - San Jose, 1988 (Box:folder 2:29)
    - San Mateo, 1987-1988; n.d. (Box:folder 2:30)
    - Santa Cruz, 1988; n.d. (Box:folder 2:31)
    - Sonoma, 1987-1988 (Box:folder 2:32)
  - California Association of AIDS Agencies (CAAA), 1988 (Box:folder 2:33)
  - California Area Health Education Center (AHEC) System, 1987 (Box:folder 2:34)
  - California Medical Association, 1983; 1987-1988 (Box:folder 2:35)
  - California Nurses Association, 1988 (Box:folder 2:36)
  - California Public-Private Partnership Commission, 1986 (Box:folder 2:37)
  - University of California (Box:folder 2:38-41)
    - General AIDS Activities, 1987 (Box:folder 2:38)
    - UC Berkeley AIDS Activities, 1985-1988 (Box:folder 2:39)
    - UC Davis AIDS Activities, 1987-1988 (Box:folder 2:40)
    - UCLA AIDS Activities, 1983-1988 (Box:folder 2:41)
- San Francisco City and County, 1983-1989; 1993; Series 2; 1 carton 46 folders
  This series consists of materials related to AIDS services, policy, and information within the city and county of San Francisco. These include both city and county government agencies and community organizations, and the interface between them. Materials include newspaper clippings, scientific articles, correspondence, reports, budgets, statistics, publicity materials, and publications.
  Organized roughly alphabetically, the series starts with AIDS Reported Cases (consisting of monthly reports from the San Francisco Department of Public Health) and ends with University of California San Francisco (UCSF) AIDS Activities. The two largest categories in this series are AIDS Service Delivery System and the City and County Agencies and Commissions.
  The AIDS Service Delivery System folders are arranged alphabetically by community organizations, and include AIDS/ARC Vigil, Castro Lions Club, Haight Ashbury Free Medical Clinic, Latino AIDS Project, Operation Concern, Project Inform, Project Open Hand, and the Shanti Project, among others. The three largest sets of folders are for the San Francisco AIDS Foundation (SFAF), the Stop AIDS Project, and the Women's AIDS Network (WAN). Three oversize posters have been remove from the Multicultural Prevention Resource Center folder and place in a portfolio folder (P/1) housed with the collection.
  The City and County Agencies and Commissions files, which are also arranged roughly alphabetically, include multiple folders covering the San Francisco Health Commission, the Department of Public Health and San Francisco General Hospital, as well as folders on Health Resources and Services Administration AIDS Proposal, HIV Antibody Testing - Alternative Test Sites, Human Rights Commission, and the Public Health Services Hospital. Please note the History of AIDS Service Delivery System and the Epidemiology of AIDS which has subfolders on Intravenous (IV) Drug Use and on Sexually Transmitted Diseases (STDs). One folder of San Francisco General Hospital materials "Utilization Review" has been restricted. The Ward 5A/5B and Ward 86 folders contain press releases, manuals, short reports and newspaper articles.
  Other files include AIDS Advisory Groups and Task Forces (includes a folder on the Mayor's Task Force), AIDS Minority Issues, AIDS Perinatal Guidelines, AIDS Planning Activities, and AIDS Research Projects (information on the Association for Women's AIDS Research and Education (AWARE), AIDS School Guidelines and Clinical Study).
  - AIDS Reported Cases (Monthly DPH Reports), 1985-1988 (Box:folder 2:42-43)
  - AIDS Advisory Groups and Task Forces (Box:folder 2:44-45)
    - Mayor's Task Force, 1984-1987 (Box:folder 2:44)
    - Other, 1986-1988 (Box:folder 2:45)
  - AIDS Minority Issues, 1987-1988 (Box:folder 2:46)
  - AIDS Perinatal Guidelines, 1986 (Box:folder 2:47)
  - Positive Action Healthcare Press Conference, 1988 (Box:folder 2:48)
  - AIDS Planning Activities (Box:folder 2:49-50)
    - Preliminary Report, 1986 (Box:folder 2:49)
    - Revised Report, 1987 (Box:folder 2:50)
  - AIDS Politics (Clippings, New Yorker Articles), 1983; 1987-1988 (Box:folder 2:51)
  - AIDS Research Projects (Box:folder 2:52-54)
    - AWARE (Association for Women's AIDS Research and Education), 1986 (Box:folder 2:53)
    - AIDS School Guidelines, 1986; 1988 (Box:folder 2:54)
    - Clinic Study, n.d. (Box:folder 2:55)
  - AIDS Service Delivery System (Box:folder 2:55-3:9)
    - AIDS/ARC Vigil, 1986-1988 (Box:folder 2:55)
    - AIDS Emergency Fund, 1988 (Box:folder 2:56)
    - AIDS Healing Alliance, 1988 (Box:folder 2:57)
    - AIDS Health Project, 1984-1986 (Box:folder 2:58)
    - AIDS Homecare and Hospice Program/VNA (Visiting Nurses Association), 1986-1987 (Box:folder 2:59)
    - Asian AIDS Project, 1988 (Box:folder 2:60)
    - AVERI (AIDS Virus Education and Research Institute) (Box:folder 2:61)
    - Castro Lions Club, 1987 (Box:folder 2:62)
    - Catholic Social Services, 1987 (Box:folder 2:63)
    - Coming Home, 1987 (Box:folder 2:64)
    - Haight Ashbury Free Medical Clinic, 1984; 1987 (Box:folder 2:65)